we can start to put a crack in the
schema the schema is certain that this
is the way it is and nothing will change
it but if we can put a crack in that
Foundation perhaps that we can create
change the reason I've learned how to do
these better is because I've done all of
these worse than probably anybody will
do them if you had some sort of
traumatic experience you've likely
created what's called a maladaptive
schema that you're not even aware of
anymore can still be limiting you
challenging you and making it hard for
you to be successful today so on this
video I'm gonna break down some schemas
for you schema psychologists have
discovered that there's essentially five
different types of early maladaptive
schemas that are likely to form in early
childhood that can dominate you later
when you're an adult and of these five
there are 18 subcategories of schemas so
let's break down the five types first
there's disconnection there's impaired
autonomy Empire limits other
directedness and then there's hyper
vigilance so if you're struggling with
any of your life chances are there is a
maladaptive schema that will fall under
one of these five types so let's look at
disconnection first I've found a lot of
people that I've worked with they fall
under the disconnection of either
abandonment mistrust deprivation shame
and isolation so abandonment looks like
this as they have a chronic anxiety
about losing something or someone that's
close to them because probably at some
point in time in their life they reach
for someone and they weren't there and
they interpreted that as don't get
attached because it could go away just
like that on the other side of it
there's these exaggerated expectations
that eventually everyone will leave them
some of the ways you see this behavior
exhibited is clinginess is neediness is
controlling jealousy and so one of the
ways that this helped me is when I'd see
this types of behavior I wouldn't take
it so personal I get where this is
coming from doesn't mean I have to be
okay with it but it means that I can
have a deeper understanding of that
individual and more of an appreciation
of the experiences that that individual
has now this allows empathy empathy is
the Kryptonite to resistance of change
number two is mistrust you'll see these
people exhibit paranoia and look at
everybody else's untrustworthies who
think everyone's out to get them they
will even manipulate and lie because
they feel like the other person is going
to lie and manipulate and so they better
do it first as a means of
self-protection so when I'm working with
clients like this we lean into the
mistrust we get them to mistrust their
own false beliefs number three
deprivation so these are people that
have shut off ignored or completely
somehow blocked off their own emotional
needs I had some of these issues myself
where emotions were a sign of weakness
and if I could shut them off and think
only logically then I can make better
decisions so when I'm looking at clients
that they're full drive logic and
they're shut off emotionally I
understand that we have to work very
cautiously around any emotionally
charged situations but at the same time
there's a way that we can present
emotional logic as I call it emotion can
be accessed from the framework of logic
and that's very interesting because most
people create this false dichotomy where
logic is over here and emotion is over
there and none of those two mixed
together so we can have logical
communication about emotions we can have
emotional Communications about logic or
for shame something is wrong or
defective with the self they're fearful
that these defects can be exposed and
they're hypersensitive to criticism it
wasn't very obvious to me until I got
older you don't have to do anything for
unconditional love if you can run
somebody through a thought exercise
where they de-personalize themselves in
this situation and look at it from
somebody else's perspective this is
where we can start to put a crack in the
schema so if there's a lot of deep shame
going on here with a client I am going
to be extra careful with when I give
them critical feedback this doesn't mean
we treat everybody with Kitty gloves and
bubble wrap because then we don't create
resilience but it just means before I
can help somebody I gotta connect with
them before I connect with them I have
to understand them and this is one of
the ways in which I understood them so
until we work with that we're not going
to really help somebody isolation so
this is the last one under this category
is you don't feel like you belong
anywhere you feel different alien from
everyone else around you you see this
with a lot of people that are socially
anxious something happened early on
where it didn't feel right and it never
got correct and now this person doesn't
even feel comfortable in their own skin
and so when I see somebody who feels
like they're misaligned or disconnected
then we are very very careful in how we
create a communication framework because
all communication is predicated around
connection one of the easiest ways in
order to do this is to start somebody
out by piling on things that they can do
in isolation a lot of creative work is
very lonely I wrote this book here one
to many you should buy it it's many many
many hours alone if I see a client who
tends to be isolation I want to load
that client up at first with a lot of
things that they can do on their own and
then when they come back to me I can
begin to understand them so they feel
there's a little bit connection now
let's talk about the second type early
maladaptive schema which is impaired
autonomy and this is dependence
vulnerability in meshmen and failure
these are the subcategories under
impaired autonomy so the first one
dependence is you're unable to make
decisions you have trouble organizing
and completing daily tasks your last
individual voice and intuition this is
usually formed early on because you had
somebody take care of everything for you
to a detrimental degree if somebody else
is making all your decisions for you
then that can be very dangerous my dad
when he had a stroke he lost a sense of
autonomy where other people started
doing things for them and some people
best intention started to do too much
for him so observing these people that
have this dependence is you breed a set
of dependents to you under the right new
circumstances make them dependent on you
but they have to do X Y and Z and do one
two and three in order to get that
dependence second one is vulnerability
these are individuals that fear that
there's an impending doom they have an
exaggeration of a perception that
terrible things are going to happen to
them and that more importantly they'll
be unable to protect themselves from it
and so what we have to do most often
overload that sense of that impending
doom when a client starts to run that
way with me I'd be like yeah we should
just stop what matters anyway you create
this thing and you don't create this
thing somebody's gonna break in they're
gonna steal it they're going to deface
it they're going to blow it up it's all
going to go to hell isn't it and then I
get them to start to reflect on when do
we know it's appropriate to be concerned
and that's really powerful enmeshment I
see this a lot this unstable sense of
self where do I end and where does
somebody else start this inability to
feel whole without somebody else when I
see people that are highly unaware of
themselves I say okay I have to frame
this in a way that's not about the self
then over time how can I get them to
start being more assertive with the self
so I can really grow them up and power
them and that's really effective and
then failure people afraid that no
matter what they're doing to do they're
going to fail in life these are the
people that are prone to self-sabotage
often they put in massive effort to
overcome these feelings of bailing and
lack and the inability to be loved just
for who they are I have attempted to put
so much effort in to overcome these
feelings of failure by showing and
proving that I could achieve the problem
with that has come from the perspective
of you're running away from something
and no matter what it is when you're
running away from something there's
tension there's fear it's stressful I
want them to run away away from
something and run towards something to
start with third type called impaired
limits there's only two here is
grandiosity and insufficient control
most people something bad happens to
them they take it personal as a
deficiency but in some instances like
with grandiosity here people feel
Superior to others they focus only on
their strengths they minimize their
flaws this can be created as a
maladaptive schema in households where
they have been raised by others to feel
they are superior these are pretty easy
people for me to deal with if I have to
make them feel they're better than me to
get it all day long but along the way I
also realize that if I give in to that
they're going to operate in ways that
are going to be counterproductive to
them long term and so working on helping
them understand and measure what is
important what isn't important
regardless of the individual more on
values Less on ego and sorting that
stuff out being a little bit more loose
in the framework knowing that they don't
respond to rules or developing rules
that I know they will intentionally
violate but in a way that's powerful and
then there's second one here is
insufficient control pulsive unreliable
disorganized they have trouble enduring
discomfort before they tap out they
focus mostly on short-term gratification
with these individuals my number one
strategy is I will give them short-term
gratification of a very short-term plans
and then we can build this tension of
well I want to do more and this helps
counteract some of the schema of this
insufficient control and then over time
when you step back and you analyze it
see you did this you couldn't do this
before and then we can update the schema
potentially other directedness is
another top level maladaptive early
schema and this manifests itself with
subjugation self-sacrifice and approval
subjugation this is where one's own
needs are not as important so you just
suppress your needs to avoid rejection
and you end up feeling Weak and
Powerless one of the ways that I help
clients there is I get them to Advocate
their own needs by being deliberately
naive like what do you want is that
really what you want I'm not sure if
that's what you want or not so they get
frustrated and then they start to
vocalize it so this is one of the ways
you can deal with these clients is start
to get them to advocate for their own
needs by being intentionally dense now
the other one that goes along with
subjugation is self-sacrifice and this
was me to a team I was putting the needs
of others ahead of myself and I thought
this was a good thing one day my
therapist she says you ever heard of the
drama triangle there is the persecutor
there is the victim and then there is
The Rescuer and I always thought I was
styling in my life because I was never
the persecutor I never go out and
intentionally put other people down to
make myself feel better and never seen
myself as the victim I would say listen
a bad thing might have happened to me
but it doesn't have to Define me turns
out I was a rescuer I'm going to put
myself last I'm gonna put everybody else
first and then that's how I will be
first now these people are they're often
very stressed and overwhelmed because
they give too much of themselves to
everybody else and then they break down
this is really easy to work with these
clients I get them to start to put my
needs first as opposed to their needs
and my needs are for them to take care
of themselves for them to create
boundaries for them to know when it's
okay to help other people and when it's
not okay to help others people approval
is the last one in this category which
is self-worth based on the opinions of
others the desire to fit in focusing
oftentimes on money status appearance
and really a lack of sense of self self
is defined by achievement by notoriety
by a power by a class for me these are
very easy people to work with and I can
allow them a situation to fit in because
if we put the same type of people
together who stand out in the same ways
they will fit in with each other so I
attempt to do more of that as well for
them to understand that they can fit in
but they don't have to fit in by
conforming to what the status quo is
literally fitting in by standing out and
then there's hyper vigilance and this
has the four categories of negativity
inhibition unrelenting-ness and
punitiveness negativity is Obsession
about not making mistakes chronic
anxiety and rumination of the future I
have some of this the obsession over not
making mistakes and it's really harmed
me and others in my life along the way
because if you did 19 things right but
you missed the 20th the focus is on what
you missed now not on what you did and
you start to feel really crummy because
there's always faults and the
obsessiveness over not making these
mistakes and the chronic anxiety
associated with the potential of making
mistakes it can make you very successful
High achiever but very emptying inside I
learned this from Dan Sullivan he says
the gain not the Gap so where you're at
right now where you want to go is the
gap where you were vis-a-vis where
you're at that's the game focusing as
much on if not more on the gain as
opposed to the Gap can help counteract
some of this but also just bringing in
more into the now what's perfect about
the present inhibition this is the
person who values the self-control very
little playfulness very strict very
reserved and in this particular case we
start with this ability to be highly
structured and to be very strict and
then we pointed at activities that are
spontaneous how do we be spontaneous in
the strictest way possible and that's
very fun because what people realize is
it's not this or that it can be both we
can bring playfulness into strictness we
can bring strictness into playfulness
you gotta meet them with that tone if
you come in animated hot and heavy and
excited and pumped up and they're
reserved you mismatched them you've lost
them right so you take that very somber
tone okay this is what's going to happen
there's unrelenting this which is the
strive to meet rigorous extreme
standards perfectionism Obsession to
detail highly critical of self and
others a lot of entrepreneurs they fall
into these categories and you gotta
realize that perfectionism leads to pain
every single time perfectionism is the
ultimate imperfect action and
imperfection is the True Perfection of
The Human Condition now I can't lay that
conclusion down on clients immediately
when they come to the table they'll kick
it out of their schema immediately so
instead we allow them the rigorousness
in a way that can create flexibility an
impunitiveness the very last one here
these are the people that believe that
mistakes should be punished not forgiven
they're very intolerant of others and
really ultimately intolering themselves
they downplay the circumstances and they
upplay the characteristics in the
entrepreneur was like all the customers
are lazy and they never get anything
done uh we see this a lot with cancel
culture where people they take Delight
in other people being punished and they
never give them any forgiveness and if
that person somehow bounces back there's
a spitefulness that hangs over that
person by the mob that is Twitter I'm
not saying that you should automatically
forgive somebody immediately when
they've done harm to you I had a client
where he kept saying I understand you're
the marketing expert but you wanted
reassurance before they signed up as a
client and I was having my assistant
deal with this I just kept saying take
it away from them take it away from him
he's like I just need to know if Jason
can do this I always told her to say the
same thing I don't think you're ready
when you're ready let me know and then
you come back again and then he finally
signed up and I was very forthright with
him on the call so you shift the focus
on outcome you shift the focus more on
insight and that can help in these
situations so there you go a video deep
dive for you on schemas I wanted to
bring this to you because most people
don't talk about it and also a lot of
people in this world are unaware of it
and the people in the schema World they
seem to be stuck in this game of World
so this is a bridge between the two
hopefully these have helped you with
considering looking at and examining
your own schemas and maybe updating some
of them if nothing else I'm sure it's
going to help you with your
communication with others because a lot
of us we come to the table as damaged
goods and so if we can finesse around
that and heal that and help that and
communicate to that we've become better
and so does the other person I'll see
you in the next video